<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-15"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Documentation</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <p>For downloading ConExp and hint for installation use the menue item Download.
         </p>
    <section>
      <title>Working with Concept Explorer</title>
      <p>The ConExp user interface consists of the following parts:</p>
      <ul>
      <li>The <em>Menu</em> which is self-explanatory.</li>
      <li>The <em>Main toolbar</em> which contains buttons for global application operation as there are:
          <ul>
          <li>Create a new document;</li>
          <li>Open;</li>
          <li>Save;</li>
          <li>Compute the number of formal concepts;</li>
          <li>Compute the concept lattice;</li>
          <li>Perform the attribute exploration;</li>
          <li>Calculate the Duquenne-Guigues set of implications;</li>
          <li>Calculate association rules;</li>
          </ul>
additionally we have to mention the combo box which allows to select the update mode for the document components that are computed from the formal context (concept lattice, set of implications and association rules). Currently two update modes are supported. Those are <em>re-computation</em> of the affected components or <em>clear</em> them. The latter mode is recommended when changing the context reasonably. After realisation of those changes the appropriate operations can be reoptained for the new context.
In the case of many changes the other option would cause a re-computation for every single alteration of the context and may lead to computational expenses if the context is big or dense.</li>
      <li>The <em>main pane</em> consists of the following items: </li>
          <ul>
          <li><em>Document-tree</em>: It displays the structure of the current document and allows to navigate between different views (i.e. context, concept lattice, implications and association rules).</li>
          <li><em>Option-pane</em>: It allows to edit different options corresponding to the actual view.</li>
          <li><em>View-pane</em>: It contains the display for the current view. There is a toolbar with specific operations for each view.</li>
          </ul>
      <li>Statusbar</li>
      </ul>
      <strong>Creating a new document</strong>
      <p>When starting ConExp a new document is created. Alternatively, one can create a new document by pressing the button <em>New context</em> on main toolbar or selecting the menu item <em>New</em> in <em>Files</em> menu. If a user chooses to open a new document, while working with another that contains unsaved changes, he is asked to save it (or to cancel creating the new document) before creating the new document.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Concept Lattices and handling the line diagram</title>
      <p>
         </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Working with implication bases</title>
      <p>
         </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
