<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-15"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>References and related projects</title>
  </header> 
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>FCA, mathematical foundations</title>
      <p>For learning more about Formal Concept Analysis we recommand the book by Bernhard Ganter and Rudolf Wille <em>Formal Concept Analysis, Mathematical Foundations</em>, Springer, 1999.</p>
    </section> 
    <section>
      <title>FCA on the web</title>
      <p>For information on the theory behind ConExp we refer to one of the folling pages:</p>
      <ul>
          <li> <link href="http://www.math.tu-dresden.de/~ganter/fba.html"><em>The Dresden Formal Concept Analysis Page</em> by Bernhard Ganter </link> and</li>
          <li> <link href="http://www.upriss.org.uk/fca/fca.html"><em>A Formal Concept Analysis Homepage</em> by Uta Priss.</link></li>
      </ul>
    </section> 
    <section>
      <title>Articles about Concept Explorer</title>
      <p>Serhiy A. Yevtushenko. System of data analysis "Concept Explorer".
         (In Russian). Proceedings of the 7th national conference on Artificial
Intelligence KII-2000, p. 127-134, Russia, 2000. <link href="./ConExp-2000.pdf">ConExp-2000.pdf(317 K)</link>
            This is a first article about Concept Explorer.
      </p>

      <p>Serhiy A. Yevtushenko. Algorithms for drawing line diagrams. (In Russian).
          Proceedings of the Russian National Congress on Artificial Intelligence ICAI-2001.
          <link href="DrawingLineDiagrams-ICAI2001.pdf">DrawingLineDiagrams-ICAI2001.pdf(453 K)</link></p>
          <p>Abstract of the article: Formal Concept Analysis is a powerful method of data analysis.
        Visualization of dependencies in FCA is performed by means of
        linear diagrams of concept lattices.
        Different approaches for drawing linear diagrams are reviewed.
        Results of comparisons of several algorithms are presented.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Presentations</title>

        <dl>
            <dt>Algoritms for drawing line diagrams (In Russian). ICAI-2001 presentation </dt>
            <dd> <link href="./DrawingLineDiagrams-presentation.pdf">DrawingLineDiagrams-presentation.pdf (846 K    )</link>
 </dd>
            <dt>Darmstadt presentation for Intellectics group(August 2001)</dt>
                <dd><link href="./AlgConSet.pdf">AlgConSet.pdf(306 K)</link>
                    This presentation contains among other things pseudo-code
                    for the GRAIL algorithm for computing concept lattices used in ConExp.
                </dd>
        </dl>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
